[REBIRTH]
[환생]
[Episode 22]
[22회]
Urgent dispatch!
긴급 파견!
Great victory at Longyin Pass!
용음관에서의 대승리!
Qiao won.
차오가 이겼다.
Qiao won!
차오가 이겼다!
Look!
바라보다!
This is the victory report!
승리보고입니다!
Which one of you pushed for peace back then?
당신 중 누구 그땐 평화를 외쳤나요?
Aren't you ashamed of yourselves?
스스로 부끄럽지 않나요?
Was it you?
당신이었나요?
Your Majesty,
폐하,
it wasn't me.
그건 내가 아니었어.
Qiao has achieved extraordinary merit.
Qiao는 특별한 공로를 달성했습니다.
I'll appoint her as the Left General of Cavalry!
내가 그 사람을 임명할게 좌익 기병대 장군으로!
Your Majesty,
폐하,
that is my post.
그건 내 게시물이야.
Then, Right General of Cavalry!
그렇다면 오른쪽 기병대장군!
That is General Li Qi's post.
이것이 Li Qi 장군의 게시물입니다.
Right, right.
그렇죠, 그렇죠.
I must think of an even grander title
더 거창한 제목이 생각나야 하는데
for her.
그녀를 위해.
-Your Highness.
-전하.
Please rise, both of you.
두 분 다 일어나주세요.
Chu Qiao has defeated Yan Xun
Chu Qiao가 Yan Xun을 이겼습니다
and will soon return to Tangjing.
곧 Tangjing으로 돌아갈 것입니다.
We must act immediately.
우리는 즉시 행동해야 합니다.
Otherwise, once Li Ce consolidates his grip on the throne,
그렇지 않으면 일단 Li Ce 왕좌를 확고히 장악하고
it will be hard for us to make a move.
우리가 움직이기 어려울 거예요.
Are your troops ready?
당신의 군대는 준비됐나요?
They will reach the outskirts of Tangjing tonight.
그들은 도달할 것이다 오늘 밤 탕징 외곽.
With a single order from you,
귀하의 단일 주문으로
we will march straight
우리는 똑바로 행진할 거예요
into the capital!
수도로!
In recent days, we've been spreading word
최근 며칠 동안 우리는 소문을 퍼뜨렸습니다
of the Xuri Palace incident.
쉬리궁 사건.
All of Tangjing is buzzing with rumor.
탕징 전체가 소문으로 떠들썩하다.
The truth behind Crown Prince Maocheng's death
진실 마오청 왕세자의 죽음 뒤에
has come to light,
밝혀졌습니다
and the whereabouts of his heir
그리고 그의 상속인의 행방은
have thrown the city into an uproar.
도시를 소란에 빠뜨렸습니다.
Your Highness,
전하,
it's time to reveal your true identity.
이제 당신의 진짜 정체를 밝힐 시간입니다.
I served Crown Prince Maocheng
나는 마오청 왕세자를 섬겼다
and have been lying in wait until now.
그리고 지금까지 누워서 기다려 왔습니다.
For so many years, we've endured humiliation and hardship,
수년 동안 우리는 참아왔습니다. 굴욕과 고난,
waiting for the right moment.
적절한 순간을 기다리고 있습니다.
Now that moment has come.
이제 그 순간이 왔습니다.
We must strike immediately!
즉시 공격해야 합니다!
We must take advantage of the chaos
우리는 혼란을 이용해야 합니다
to reclaim what is rightfully yours, Your Highness.
되찾다 정당하게 당신의 것이 무엇입니까, 전하.
[Tangjing]
[탕징]
Your Majesty is here again,
폐하께서 다시 오셨습니다.
waiting for General Xiuli?
Xiuli 장군을 기다리고 계십니까?
This is the highest spot
이곳이 가장 높은 곳이야
in Tangjing, where you can see all the way north.
탕징에서 볼 수 있는 곳 북쪽 끝까지.
If Qiao comes back,
Qiao가 돌아오면
I'll be
나는
the first to spot her from here.
여기에서 처음으로 그녀를 발견했습니다.
Come on.
어서 해봐요.
Be careful!
조심하세요!
Thank you.
감사합니다.
Ever since General Xiuli came here,
Xiuli 장군이 여기에 온 이후로,
Your Majesty has been fond of her.
폐하께서는 그녀를 좋아하셨습니다.
Now that she's away on campaign,
이제 그녀는 캠페인 중이므로
Your Majesty worries about her every day.
폐하께서는 매일 그녀를 걱정하십니다.
If General Xiuli knew,
Xiuli 장군이 알았다면,
she would surely be moved by Your Majesty's devotion.
그 사람은 분명 감동받았을 거야 폐하의 헌신으로.
Her?
그녀의?
No way she would.
그녀는 그럴 리가 없습니다.
She only likes fighting and warfare.
그녀는 싸움과 전쟁만을 좋아합니다.
And I don't want to
그리고 난 그러고 싶지 않아
tie her down with my feelings.
그녀를 내 감정으로 묶으세요.
But
하지만
when Qiao comes back,
Qiao가 돌아오면
I'll definitely give her
꼭 그녀에게 줄게
a grand title—
거창한 제목—
something even greater than Sun Di's and Li Qi's combined.
뭔가 더 대단한 것 Sun Di와 Li Qi를 합친 것보다 더 많습니다.
To thank her for
그녀에게 감사의 말을 전하기 위해
protecting the territory of Biantang for me.
비안탕의 영토를 수호하다 나를 위해.
Li Yan,
리얀,
you read a lot.
당신은 많이 읽습니다.
Help me see
볼 수 있도록 도와주세요
if the title I've come up with is any good.
내가 생각해낸 제목이라면 괜찮습니다.
Okay.
좋아요.
Why?
왜?
I never intended to kill you,
난 당신을 죽일 생각은 없었어요
but we were destined to end up like this.
하지만 우리는 이렇게 될 운명이었어.
What a pity.
정말 안타깝습니다.
You will never get to see
넌 절대 볼 수 없을 거야
your beloved General Chu return.
사랑하는 추 장군이 돌아왔습니다.
Qiao...
챠오...
I can no longer
더 이상은 할 수 없어
protect you...
당신을 보호해주세요...
Your Highness,
전하,
5,000 imperial guards from nine city gates
9개의 성문에서 5,000명의 황실 경비병
of Tangjing
탕징
have assembled at the North Gate.
북문에 모였습니다.
A total of 200 gate sentries have been stationed
총 200개의 게이트 보초 주둔 중
at all six gates on the east and west sides,
6개 게이트 모두에서 동쪽과 서쪽에,
awaiting Your Highness's orders.
전하의 명령을 기다리고 있습니다.
Additionally,
추가적으로
garrison troops from Lingnan and Lingdong
링난(Lingnan)과 링동(Lingdong)의 수비대
have been deployed 30 li outside Tangjing.
Tangjing 외곽 30리에 배치되었습니다.
Should anything arise,
무슨 일이 생기면
they can enter the capital immediately to protect you!
그들은 즉시 수도에 들어갈 수 있다 당신을 보호하기 위해!
-Your subjects,
-당신의 과목,
-Xu Su, -Pei Jian,
-쑤 수, -페이 지안,
respectfully welcome Your Majesty!
폐하를 정중히 환영합니다!
Long live Your Majesty!
폐하 만세!
Qiao...
챠오...
I can't wait for you anymore.
나는 더 이상 당신을 기다릴 수 없습니다.
I'm way better
훨씬 나아졌어
than that stone-faced Zhuge Yue.
그 돌얼굴의 제갈월보다.
♪ The dust in the world ♪
♪ 세상의 먼지 ♪
I'm handsome, suave,
난 잘생겼고 상냥해
elegant, and graceful!
우아하고, 우아해요!
I can't spend my whole life playing the role of
평생을 보낼 수가 없어
♪ Is blown away easily by the wind ♪
역할을 하고 있어요 ♪ 바람에 쉽게 날아가 버립니다 ♪
a debauched wastrel, drowning in luxury and carnal indulgence.
방탕한 낭비자, 사치와 육신의 방종에 빠져 있습니다.
♪ Who can stay calm ♪
♪ 누가 가만히 있을 수 있겠어 ♪
I must first be able to protect myself
먼저 나 자신을 보호할 수 있어야 합니다
before I can protect the people I want to protect.
내가 사람들을 지키기 전에 나는 보호하고 싶다.
♪ And not be scared? ♪
♪ 그리고 겁먹지 않나요? ♪
♪ A slight ripple ♪
♪ 약간의 파문 ♪
What does it really feel like
정말 어떤 느낌이야
♪ Floating life hangs by a thread ♪
♪ 떠다니는 인생은 실에 매달려 있습니다 ♪
to truly love someone?
누군가를 진심으로 사랑한다는 것?
To truly love someone
누군가를 진심으로 사랑하려면
is to feel what they feel.
그들이 느끼는 것을 느끼는 것입니다.
♪ The more pulled, the softer it gets ♪
♪ 더 많이 당길수록 부드러워집니다 ♪
You can sense his happiness,
그의 행복이 느껴지네요
♪ Who dares to say forever? ♪
♪ 누가 감히 영원하다고 말하겠습니까? ♪
so naturally, you can also feel
그러면 자연스럽게 느낄 수도
the pain and struggle in his heart.
그의 마음 속의 고통과 투쟁.
♪ Let it be ♪
♪ 그대로 두세요 ♪
You would find joy through him
그를 통해 기쁨을 찾을 수 있을 거예요
and naturally feel pain through him as well.
그리고 자연스럽게 고통을 느끼죠 그것도 그를 통해서.
I, by the mandate of Heaven,
나는 하늘의 명령에 따라
reign over all under the sky!
하늘 아래 온통 통치하라!
With clear rewards and punishments,
명확한 보상과 처벌을 통해
I uphold the moral order of the realm.
나는 왕국의 도덕적 질서를 옹호합니다.
Now,
이제,
it has been found that Li Lin, Minister of Revenue,
리린(Li Lin)이라는 사실이 밝혀졌습니다. 세무부 장관,
has embezzled the treasury and engaged in malpractice for selfish ends.
국고를 횡령하고 범죄를 저질렀다 이기적인 목적을 위한 과실.
His crimes are beyond dispute, a flagrant violation of heavenly law.
그의 범죄는 논쟁의 여지가 없으며, 명백한 천법 위반이다.
By law, he is to be executed.
법에 따르면 그는 처형되어야 한다.
I hereby order the execution of his entire clan
이에 집행을 명령합니다 그의 클랜 전체 중
as a warning to all!
모두에게 경고로!
It is noon.
정오입니다.
Prepare for the execution!
처형을 준비하세요!
Mother!
어머니!
Execute!
실행하다!
Old man,
노인님,
how long are you going to keep me here?
언제까지 나를 여기에 가둬둘 건가요?
Not yet.
아직 아님.
Wait another hour until your son comes back from the imperial court
아들이 나올 때까지 한 시간 더 기다리세요 황실에서 돌아왔다
and tell us how things stand outside.
바깥 상황이 어떤지 알려주세요.
Then I'll decide.
그럼 내가 결정할게.
He's just a sixth-rank deputy commander.
그는 단지 6급 부사령관입니다.
Why did you let him go to the court?
왜 그를 법정에 보내셨나요?
Not anymore.
더 이상은 아닙니다.
I had him resign on your behalf, citing illness,
나는 당신을 대신하여 그 사람을 사임시켰습니다. 질병을 언급하며
and hand over your military tally
그리고 군사 기록을 넘겨주세요
as a show of loyalty to Li Yan.
Li Yan에 대한 충성심을 표시합니다.
Li Yan has promoted him three ranks as a reward.
Li Yan이 그를 승진시켰습니다 보상으로 3등급.
He is now a General.
그는 이제 장군이 되었습니다.
You asked him to hand over my military command?
당신은 그에게 넘겨달라고 요청했습니다 내 군사 명령?
Who gives you the right to make decisions for me?
누가 당신에게 권리를 주나요? 나를 위해 결정을 내리라고?
Sun Di!
썬 디!
You're my daughter's husband.
당신은 내 딸의 남편이에요.
What you do affects not only yourself
당신이 하는 일은 당신 자신에게만 영향을 미치는 것이 아니다
but also the lives of
뿐만 아니라
my daughter and my whole clan!
내 딸과 내 일족 전체가!
At a time like this,
이런 때에는
never mind military command—
군사 명령은 신경쓰지 마세요—
as long as we can keep our lives,
우리가 생명을 유지할 수 있는 한,
even if you have to play the fool,
바보 같은 짓을 해야 한다고 해도
you must keep playing along!
계속 같이 놀아야 해!
Li Yan is nothing but a treasonous rebel who usurped the throne!
리얀은 반역적인 반역자일 뿐입니다 누가 왕위를 찬탈했는가!
I'll lead my troops
내가 군대를 이끌게
into the palace and kill him right now!
지금 당장 궁전으로 가서 그를 죽여라!
And then what?
그리고 무엇?
The late emperor is dead.
고(故) 황제가 죽었습니다.
Who will take the throne?
누가 왕위를 차지할 것인가?
Who will take charge of the overall situation in Biantang?
누가 맡을 것인가 비안탕의 전반적인 상황은요?
Or do you...
아니면...
want to become the next Li Yan?
다음 Li Yan이 되고 싶나요?
Close the door
문을 닫아
and add a few more locks.
잠금 장치를 몇 개 더 추가하세요.
No one is allowed in or out.
누구도 출입이 허용되지 않습니다.
Let this fool cool his head.
이 바보가 머리를 식히게 놔두세요.
The imperial edict of investiture has been issued.
제국의 서임 칙령 발행되었습니다.
You are now Empress.
당신은 이제 황후입니다.
Your Majesty,
폐하,
why do you put yourself through this?
왜 이런 일을 겪게 합니까?
Ask them all to leave.
모두 떠나라고 하세요.
Your Majesty...
폐하...
His Majesty has arrived!
폐하께서 오셨습니다!
Leave.
떠나다.
Chun'er,
춘어,
what's wrong?
무슨 일이야?
I've been on the throne for over a month.
나는 한 달 넘게 왕좌에 있었습니다.
Yet you still refuse to
그런데도 당신은 여전히 ​​
wear the empress's robes.
황후의 예복을 입으세요.
And you've declined to accompany me
그리고 당신은 나와 동행하기를 거부했어요
to every state banquet and ceremony.
모든 국빈 연회 및 행사에.
What exactly are you unhappy about?
정확히 어떤 점이 불만스럽나요?
You're now the most honored woman in all the world.
당신은 이제 가장 존경받는 여성이에요 전 세계에서.
All the pain you've endured before
이전에 견뎌왔던 모든 고통
is in the past.
과거입니다.
What more do you want?
무엇을 더 원하시나요?
Or is it that...
아니면 그게...
I have not treated you well?
내가 잘 대해주지 않았나요?
Li Yan.
리얀.
Who exactly are you?
당신은 정확히 누구입니까?
When I first met you,
당신을 처음 만났을 때,
you said you were just a scion of a noble family in Biantang.
넌 그냥 후예라고 했지 비안탕(Biantang)의 귀족 가문 출신.
But when I came to Tangjing with you,
하지만 내가 당신과 함께 탕징에 왔을 때,
I found out you were the Prince of Luo.
나는 당신이 루오의 왕자라는 것을 알았습니다.
I believed you,
난 당신을 믿었어요
thinking you were marginalized outside the imperial court
당신이 소외되었다고 생각 황실 밖에서
and humiliated,
그리고 굴욕감을 느꼈다
so I wanted to help you reclaim a little of
그래서 나는 당신을 돕고 싶었어요 조금 회수해
the dignity a royal descendant should have.
존엄성 왕족의 후손이 있어야 합니다.
But then you transformed
그런데 당신은 변신했어요
into who you are now.
당신이 지금 누구인지.
It's not that I refuse to be your empress.
내가 당신의 황후가 되기를 거부하는 것은 아닙니다.
I'm just bewildered—
난 그냥 어리둥절한 것 뿐이야—
who are you, really?
당신은 정말 누구입니까?
It feels as though I've never truly known you.
마치 한 번도 그런 적 없는 것 같은 느낌이 들어요 당신을 정말로 알았습니다.
Will there come a day
언젠가 올까
when I stand atop the walls
내가 벽 위에 섰을 때
of Tangjing in my empress's ceremonial robes,
탕징의 내 황후의 예복을 입고
only to die
죽을 수밖에 없어
in your arms the very next moment?
바로 다음 순간에 네 품에 안겨?
Zhao Chun'er,
조춘얼,
you think you are the only one
당신이 유일한 사람이라고 생각하는군요
who has suffered grievances and pain?
누가 원망과 고통을 겪었습니까?
If you don't want to
원하지 않는다면
wear the empress's attire,
황후의 옷을 입으세요
I won't force you.
나는 당신에게 강요하지 않을 것입니다.
Biantang is in chaos right now.
지금 비안탕은 혼란에 빠졌습니다.
Just stay in the palace and rest well.
그냥 궁전에 있으면서 편히 쉬세요.
[Ministry of War Office]
[국군청]
Why are you here?
당신은 왜 여기에 있습니까?
How is General Xiuli?
슈리 장군은 어떤가요?
My situation is a bit complicated right now.
내 상황은 지금은 좀 복잡해요.
Lord Sun.
썬님.
You know
아시죠
what this is, right?
이게 뭐죠?
Minister Xu!
쉬 장관님!
Bad news!
나쁜 소식!
Sun Di...
순 디...
Sun Di has mobilized troops from the Southeastern Guard Camp,
손디가 군대를 동원했다 남동부 경비캠프에서
50 li east of the city, into the palace!
성에서 동쪽으로 50리, 왕궁으로!
He may be plotting rebellion!
그는 반란을 계획하고 있을지도 모릅니다!
Sun Di?
썬디?
The military tally is in my hands.
군사 집계는 내 손에 있습니다.
How did he mobilize anyone?
그는 어떻게 누군가를 동원했는가?
Go assemble the imperial guards immediately.
가서 조립해라 즉시 제국 경비대.
I'll go to the palace to protect the Emperor myself.
나는 궁전에 갈 것이다 황제를 보호하기 위해.
Yes, sir!
네, 선생님!
Minister Xu!
쉬 장관님!
The Ministry of War has just sent word
전쟁부가 방금 전갈을 보냈습니다
that someone broke into the office last night,
누군가가 사무실에 침입했다고 어젯밤
and the military tally of the Southeastern Guards is missing!
그리고 군사 집계 남동부 경비대가 사라졌습니다!
Come with me!
나와 함께 가자!
You told me once
나한테 한 번 말했지
that in this deep palace,
이 깊은 궁전에서는
power and the throne
권력과 왕좌
matter far more than blood ties.
혈연보다 훨씬 더 중요하다.
At first, I didn't understand.
처음에는 이해가 되지 않았습니다.
I even blamed you for not wanting to acknowledge me.
난 심지어 널 비난했어 나를 인정하고 싶지 않아서.
I'll take my leave.
나는 떠날 것이다.
But now I understand.
하지만 이제는 이해합니다.
And I've done it—
그리고 난 해냈어요—
even better than you, Mother.
당신보다 훨씬 나아요, 어머니.
And I understand it more deeply than you.
그리고 나는 당신보다 그것을 더 깊이 이해합니다.
Mother,
어머니,
if you were still alive
네가 아직 살아 있었다면
and could see who I am today,
오늘 내가 누구인지 알 수 있었네요
you would probably be
너는 아마도
proud of me.
내가 자랑스럽다.
I knew
난 알고 있었어
Xu Su's men couldn't kill you.
Xu Su의 부하들은 당신을 죽일 수 없었습니다.
I knew you would come back for me.
나는 당신이 나를 위해 돌아올 것이라는 것을 알았습니다.
You knew I'd come to kill you
내가 널 죽이러 올 줄 알았지
for Li Ce?
리세에게?
I knew.
나는 알고 있었다.
But I'm not afraid.
하지만 나는 두렵지 않습니다.
Because this is my fate.
이것이 내 운명이니까.
Li Ce was not your enemy.
리세는 당신의 적이 아니었습니다.
Why couldn't you let him go?
왜 그를 놓아줄 수 없었나요?
From the very beginning,
처음부터
it was always one or the other— Li Ce or me.
항상 둘 중 하나였어요. Li Ce 또는 나.
If I hadn't killed him,
내가 그를 죽이지 않았다면
one day he would've discovered my true identity
어느 날 그는 발견했을 것이다 내 진짜 정체성
and moved to eliminate me all the same.
그리고 나를 모두 제거하려고 움직였습니다.
He wouldn't.
그는 그렇지 않을 것입니다.
Move aside!
옆으로 비켜!
I need to enter the palace to see His Majesty!
궁전에 들어가야 해요 폐하를 만나러!
Lord Xu,
쑤 경,
I've received His Majesty's order to protect him.
나는 폐하의 명령을 받았습니다 그를 보호하기 위해.
No one is allowed to enter the palace.
누구도 궁전에 들어갈 수 없습니다.
Go back.
돌아가세요.
Sun Di,
순 디,
you're no longer the Left General of Cavalry.
당신은 더 이상 없습니다 기병대의 좌익 장군.
Your son resigned on your behalf two days ago,
당신의 아들이 당신을 대신하여 사임했습니다. 이틀 전
and His Majesty approved it!
폐하께서 승인하셨습니다!
Otherwise, do you think you and your family
그렇지 않으면 생각하십니까? 당신과 당신의 가족
could still live peacefully in Biantang?
비안탕에서는 아직도 평화롭게 살 수 있을까요?
The military tally is here.
군사 집계가 여기에 있습니다.
I'm acting on His Majesty's verbal decree.
나는 폐하의 구두 법령에 따라 행동하고 있습니다.
There are rebels among the imperial guards in the capital.
제국 근위대 중에 반란군이 있습니다 수도에서.
I was ordered to mobilize troops from the Southeast Camp
군대를 동원하라는 명령을 받았어요 남동쪽 캠프에서
into the capital to protect the Imperial City.
수도로 임페리얼 시티를 보호하기 위해.
By His Majesty's order, none may enter without imperial authorization.
폐하의 명령에 따라 누구도 들어갈 수 없습니다 제국의 허가 없이.
How dare you, Sun Di!
감히, Sun Di!
You broke into the Ministry of War Office
당신은 전쟁부 사무실에 침입했습니다
and stole the military tally of the Southeastern Guards!
그리고 군사 기록을 훔쳤어요 남동부 경비대의!
This is a capital crime that warrants the execution of your entire clan!
이는 다음과 같은 중대한 범죄입니다. 클랜 전체를 처형하세요!
Lord Xu, you must be talking nonsense.
Xu 경님, 말도 안되는 소리를 하고 계시군요.
His Majesty handed the military tally to me personally.
폐하께서 군사 집계를 건네주셨습니다 나한테는 개인적으로.
You must have forgotten.
당신은 잊어버렸나 봐요.
All soldiers, listen to my command!
모든 군인들이여, 내 명령을 들어라!
You're Biantang's soldiers!
당신들은 비안탕의 병사들이군요!
I'm the Minister of War!
나는 전쟁부 장관이다!
The criminal Sun Di has stolen the military tally
범죄자 순디 군사 기록을 훔쳤어요
and committed treason!
반역죄를 저질렀습니다!
Seize him immediately!
즉시 그를 붙잡아라!
The military tally is here!
군사 집계가 여기에 있습니다!
I am the General of Cavalry!
나는 기병대 장군이다!
Who dares move?
누가 감히 움직이겠는가?
Li Ce
리 세
was never worthy of this dragon robe from the day he was born!
이 드래곤 로브를 입을 자격이 없었어 그가 태어난 날부터!
General Chu,
추 장군,
this is a family matter between Li Ce and me.
이건 가족 문제야 Li Ce와 나 사이.
You didn't have to get involved.
당신은 참여할 필요가 없었습니다.
Li Ce helped you,
Li Ce가 도움을 주었습니다.
but he also did it to use you.
하지만 그 사람도 당신을 이용하려고 그런 짓을 한 거예요.
If you hadn't helped him,
당신이 그를 도와주지 않았다면
he wouldn't have sat on that throne for even a single day.
그 사람은 그 왕좌에 앉지 않았을 거야 단 하루라도.
If you hadn't saved him,
당신이 그를 구하지 않았다면,
he might have been killed by my mother long ago.
그 사람은 죽었을지도 몰라 오래전에 어머니가.
Yes.
예.
She was also his mother.
그녀는 또한 그의 어머니였습니다.
Come to think of it,
생각해 보니,
we were true brothers by blood.
우리는 피를 나눈 진정한 형제였습니다.
Did you not help Li Ce
Li Ce를 도와주지 않았나요
simply to rebuild your Xiuli Army?
단순히 Xiuli 군대를 재건하기 위해?
You and Li Ce were allies, true enough,
당신과 Li Ce는 동맹자였습니다. 사실이죠.
but I can give you all of that too.
하지만 나도 그 모든 것을 당신에게 줄 수 있어요.
In the royal family,
왕실에서는
even blood ties mean nothing—
혈연조차도 아무 의미가 없어—
let alone the meager friendship between you two.
빈약한 우정은 말할 것도 없고 너희 둘 사이.
How can
어떻게
friendship be more reliable than interests?
우정이 더 믿음직스러워 관심사보다?
What do you want?
당신은 무엇을 원하세요?
General Xiuli?
슈리 장군?
Prince of Xiuli?
슈리왕자?
Or Queen Xiuli?
아니면 Xiuli 여왕?
An assassin is in the palace!
암살자가 궁전에 있습니다!
Soldiers, heed my command—
군인들이여, 내 명령을 따르십시오—
enter the palace to protect His Majesty!
폐하를 보호하기 위해 궁전으로 들어가세요!
General Chu,
추 장군,
we can make a deal.
우리는 거래를 할 수 있습니다.
Li Yan,
리얀,
Li Ce was not
Li Ce는
a bargaining chip for power.
권력을 위한 협상카드.
He was my friend.
그는 내 친구였습니다.
The new Emperor Li Yan is dead.
새로운 황제 리얀이 사망했습니다.
There is no need to protect him.
그를 보호할 필요는 없습니다.
Chu Qiao has assassinated the Emperor!
초교가 황제를 암살했습니다!
Her crime is unforgivable!
그녀의 범죄는 용서받을 수 없습니다!
Kill Chu Qiao immediately!
즉시 추교를 죽여라!
Xu Su, guilty of treason and regicide,
Xu Su, 반역죄와 국왕 살해 혐의로 유죄
has already been executed!
이미 실행되었습니다!
Soldiers, hear my command!
병사들이여, 내 명령을 들어라!
Seize all of his personal guards!
그의 개인 경비원을 모두 붙잡아라!
Imperial guards who acted unknowingly
무의식적으로 행동한 황실 근위대
under Xu Su's orders—
Xu Su의 명령에 따라—
surrender,
항복,
and you will be pardoned!
그러면 당신은 용서받을 것입니다!
♪ The dust in the world ♪
♪ 세상의 먼지 ♪
♪ Is blown away easily by the wind ♪
♪ 바람에 쉽게 날아가 버립니다 ♪
Qiao is the world-renowned General Chu.
Qiao는 세계적으로 유명한 추 장군입니다.
♪ Who can stay calm ♪
♪ 침착할 수 있는 사람 ♪
"General Chu Meets the Crown Prince of Biantang By Chance—
"추장군이 만난다 우연히 변당왕세자—
♪ And not be scared? ♪
♪ 그리고 겁먹지 않나요? ♪
Fake Drama Turns Into Real Fate."
가짜 드라마가 진짜 운명으로 변한다."
♪ A slight ripple ♪
♪ 약간의 파문 ♪
♪ Floating life hangs by a thread ♪
♪ 떠다니는 인생은 실에 매달려 있습니다 ♪
♪ The more pulled, the softer it gets ♪
♪ 더 많이 당길수록 부드러워집니다 ♪
Qiao...
챠오...
♪ Who dares to say forever? ♪
♪ 누가 감히 영원하다고 말하겠습니까? ♪
♪ Let it be ♪
♪ 그대로 두세요 ♪
♪ Grudges and grace were never meant to be ♪
♪ 원한과 은혜 절대 그럴 운명은 아니었어 ♪
Qiao,
차오,
I'm giving these 3,000 imperial guards to you.
나는주고있다 이 3,000명의 황실 경비병을 당신에게 드립니다.
♪ Why must you take and demand so much? ♪
♪ 왜 그렇게 많은 것을 취하고 요구해야 합니까? ♪
They shall guard you just as they
그들은 그들처럼 당신을 보호할 것입니다
♪ Go weaving ♪
♪ 짜러 가세요 ♪
protect me.
나를 보호해 주세요.
♪ Grand and glorious excuses ♪
♪ 위대하고 영광스러운 변명들 ♪
Li Ce,
리세,
I haven't fulfilled my promise to you yet.
나는 아직 당신과의 약속을 이행하지 않았습니다.
♪ We once beheld ♪
♪ 우리는 한때 ♪
♪ A mirage on earth ♪
♪ 지구상의 신기루 ♪
♪ Beauty never ♪
♪ 아름다움은 결코 ♪
♪ Lasts for long ♪
♪ 오래 지속됩니다 ♪
[Mihe Abode]
[미허 거주지]
♪ No matter how a jade is carved ♪
♪ 옥을 어떻게 조각하든지 ♪
♪ It's just a stone ♪
♪ 그냥 돌일 뿐이야 ♪
♪ It will eventually disappear ♪
♪ 결국에는 사라질 것입니다 ♪
Xing.
싱.
I want to avenge Li Ce.
나는 리세의 복수를 하고 싶다.
I must kill the Prince of Luo!
나는 루오왕자를 죽여야 한다!
Xing,
싱,
Li Yan is already dead.
리얀은 이미 죽었어.
You killed him with your own hands.
당신은 당신 손으로 그를 죽였습니다.
No!
아니요!
Xing.
싱.
Everything is over now.
이제 모든 것이 끝났습니다.
Li Ce has been avenged.
리세의 복수가 이루어졌습니다.
It's all in the past.
그것은 모두 과거의 일입니다.
It's all over now?
이제 다 끝났나요?
You've done
넌 해냈어
everything you could.
당신이 할 수 있는 모든 것.
And you did it well.
그리고 당신은 그것을 잘 해냈습니다.
♪ The flowers fall into the sleeves ♪
♪ 꽃이 소매 안으로 떨어졌어요 ♪
♪ They do not understand my sorrow ♪
♪ 그들은 내 슬픔을 이해하지 못한다 ♪
You can
넌 할 수 있어
♪ With a pot of wine ♪
♪ 와인 한 병과 함께 ♪
leave it all behind now.
이제 모든 것을 남겨두세요.
♪ My longing surges ♪
♪ 그리움이 솟아오른다 ♪
♪ I become haggard ♪
♪ 초췌해졌어 ♪
♪ Soft rain patters on the windowpane ♪
♪ 유리창에 부드러운 빗소리가 들린다 ♪
♪ Awakening from the dream, I no longer know what year it is ♪
♪ 꿈에서 깨어나, 이제 몇 년인지 모르겠어요 ♪
♪ My love remains ♪
♪ 내 사랑은 남아있습니다 ♪
♪ But you're already gone ♪
♪ 하지만 당신은 이미 가버렸어요 ♪
♪ What I seek in life ♪
♪ 내가 인생에서 추구하는 것 ♪
♪ Is nothing more than to look back once more ♪
♪ 그 이상은 아니다 다시 한 번 뒤를 돌아보는 것보다 ♪
♪ With the fragrance still lingering ♪
♪ 아직 향기가 남아있는 상태로 ♪
♪ In these trembling hands ♪
♪ 떨리는 손에 ♪
♪ My longing still rests ♪
♪ 내 그리움은 아직 쉬고 있어요 ♪
♪ Words left unspoken ♪
♪ 말하지 않은 말들 ♪
♪ Turn into guilt ♪
♪ 죄책감으로 변해 ♪
♪ Beneath the stars ♪
♪ 별빛 아래 ♪
♪ Rippling throughout this life ♪
♪ 평생 동안 파문이 일었다 ♪
♪ I ask the vast sky ♪
♪ 넓은 하늘에 묻습니다 ♪
♪ The wind is light, but my longing is heavy ♪
♪ 바람은 가벼워요 하지만 그리움은 무거워요 ♪
♪ How do we start over? ♪
♪ 어떻게 다시 시작하나요? ♪
♪ How do we love and hold on without parting ♪
♪ 우리는 어떻게 사랑하는가 그리고 헤어지지 말고 버텨보자 ♪
♪ Or misunderstanding each other? ♪
♪ 아니면 서로 오해하고 있는 걸까요? ♪
♪ Do not let me only understand the meaning of a fleeting glance ♪
♪ 나만 이해하게 놔두지 마세요 찰나의 의미 ♪
♪ When my eyes are red with tears ♪
♪ 눈물로 눈시울이 붉어질 때 ♪
♪ What cannot be kept, can only be sent away ♪
♪ 지킬 수 없는 것, 다른 사람에게만 보낼 수 있습니다 ♪
♪ In the end ♪
♪ 결국 ♪
♪ It can only be praised ♪
♪ 칭찬할 수밖에 없습니다 ♪
A weak ruler over a strong state
강한 국가에 대한 약한 통치자
is an omen of instability for the nation!
국가가 불안정하다는 징조입니다!
General Xiuli, Chu Qiao, is hereby conferred
Xiuli 장군, Chu Qiao, 이로써 수여됩니다
the title of Imperial Consort Xiuli!
황제 배우자 Xiuli의 칭호!
I'll leave the 500 guards
경비병 500명을 남겨둘게요
Li Ce promised me to you.
Li Ce가 당신에게 약속했습니다.
Where have you gone now?
지금은 어디로 갔나요?
Miss!
놓치다!
I have a favor to ask of you.
당신에게 부탁할 것이 있습니다.
No matter how the royal clan schemes
왕실 일족이 아무리 계획을 세우더라도
or how chaotic the world becomes,
아니면 세상이 얼마나 혼란스러워지는지,
nothing shall ever separate us again.
그 무엇도 다시는 우리를 갈라놓지 못할 것입니다.
Don't come over.
오지 마세요.
Don't come over!
오지 마세요!